Register of the Mieczyslaw Jałowiecki Memoirs and Drawings, 1964
Hoover Institution Archives
Mieczyslaw Jałowiecki memoirs and drawings,
1964
XX170
Jałowiecki, Mieczyslaw, 1886-
8 manuscript boxes, 12 oversize boxes (9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Relates to historical events in Russia and Lithuania before, during, and after the Russian Revolution and Civil War; Poles in Lithuania; and agricultural developments in Lithuania, 1881-1939. Includes watercolor drawings and sketches of scenes and manor houses in Lithuania and Poland, as well as parts of Belarus, Ukraine, Latvia, and Estonia. Boxes 1-8 also available on microfilm (8 reels).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Boxes 1-8 also available on microfilm (8 reels).
Biographical Note
Mieczyslaw Jałowiecki was born to a prominent Polish landowning family of northern Lithuania in 1876. He studied in St. Petersburg, Riga, and several German universities, completing degrees in agriculture and agricultural economics. His career in Russian civil service, in agricultural finance, and in business, gave him the opportunity to travel and to develop an intimate knowledge of the economic and cultural landscape of Lithuania and its neighborhood. Shortly before World War I, Jałowiecki was elected president of the assembly of the nobility of northeastern Lithuania.
The war devastated the region and disrupted the lives of most of its inhabitants. Jałowiecki lost virtually everything. His ancestral Sylgudyszki, with thousands of acres of meticulously managed farmland and forests, was nationalized by the government of the newly independent Lithuania, and he moved to Poland. Because of his economic expertise and knowledge of German affairs, the Polish government appointed him to be its representative in the city of Gdansk (Danzig). Here, during 1919-20, he was able to open the port facilities to arriving American food and humanitarian relief for Poland, which was organized by Herbert Hoover. He spent the remaining interwar years farming on his wife's estate in western Poland.
World War II took him ever farther from the beloved lands of his ancestors and his youth. As a refugee in Allied London, he worked for the Polish government in exile, publishing pamphlets and textbooks on a variety of subjects. The war ended with East Central Europe under Soviet occupation and hundreds of thousands of Polish refugees unable to return to their homeland of whom Jałowiecki was one. From the standpoint of his literary and artistic legacy, these postwar London years were his most productive.
Living in very modest circumstances in his later years, he spent virtually all of his time writing his memoirs, drawing, and painting. Jałowiecki re-created the world of his youth in his sixteen-volume memoirs and more than a thousand detailed views of country manors, palaces, and landscapes of Poland, Lithuania, Latvia, Belarus, and Ukraine. Jałowiecki died in London in 1962.
Scope and Content of Collection
Mieczyslaw Jałowiecki's manuscripts and watercolors were acquired by the Hoover Archives a few years after his death in 1962. In his later years, Jałowiecki spent virtually all of his time writing his memoirs, drawing, and painting. Taking advantage of the private photographic and iconographic collections of the Polish émigré community, the resources of the British Museum, and his own near-photographic memory, Jałowiecki re-created the world of his youth, in his sixteen-volume memoirs and in more than a thousand detailed views of country manors, palaces, and landscapes of Poland, Lithuania, Latvia, Belarus, and Ukraine. Each view is accompanied by detailed information on former owners and, whenever possible, builders and architects.
Because of the massive destruction wreaked by World War II, the many decades of deliberate neglect under communism, and limited surviving documentation, Jałowiecki's drawings have become a valuable source of information on the region's architectural heritage. In some cases, as the modest country manor of Sylgudyszki, they are the only available representations.
Access Points
Agriculture--Lithuania.; Poles--Lithuania.; Lithuania.; Lithuania--History.; Lithuania--Views.; Poland.; Poland--Views.; Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--History.; Drawings.
Container List
- Memoirs, undated. (Box 1-4)
  Describes Jałowiecki's experiences from 1881 to 1964 in sixteen volumes.
  - "Z Lat Minionych" (From Bygone Years), Tom I (Volume I) (Folder 1: 1)
    - "Dieciństwo i Szkoły" (Childhood and Schooling), Część 1 (Part 1) (Folder 1)
    - "Gaudeamus," Część 2 (Part 2) (Folder 1)
    - "Na Szerokim Świecie" (In the Wide World), Część 3 (Part 3) (Folder 1)
  - "Pierwsze Lata" (The First Years), Tom II (Volume II) (Folder 1: 2)
  - "Po Dworach i Wsi Litewskiej" (In the Manors and Village of Lithuania), Tom III (Volume III) (Folder 1: 3)
  - "Lata Przed Burzą" (The Years Before the Storm) (Folder 1)
    - Tom IV (Volume IV) (Folder 1: 4)
    - Tom V (Volume V) (Folder 2: 1)
  - "Burza" (The Storm) (Folder 2)
    - Tom VI (Volume VI) (Folder 2: 2)
    - Tom VII (Volume VII) (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Bolszewicy" (The Bolsheviks), Tom VIII (Volume VIII) (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Powrót" (The Return), Tom IX (Volume IX) (Folder 3: 1)
  - "Gdańsk" (Folder 3)
    - Tom X (Volume X) (Folder 3: 2)
    - Tom XI (Volume XI) (Folder 3: 3)
  - "Pod Znakiem Buraka i Zająca" (Under the Sign of the Beet and the Hare)
    - Tom XII (Volume XII) (Folder 3: 4)
    - Tom XIII (Volume XIII) (Folder 4: 1)
    - Tom XIV (Volume XIV) (Folder 4: 2)
    - Tom XV (Volume XV) (Folder 4: 3)
  - "Epilog" (Epilogue), Tom XVI (Volume XVI) (Folder 4: 4)
- Indices to Watercolor drawings, undated. (Box 5-7)
  Various versions of Jałowiecki's listings of his watercolor drawings.
  - Dwór Polski, Katalog, M. Jałowiecki (Folder 5: 1)
  - Katalog Kolekcji, M. Jałowiecki (Folder 5: 2)
  - Egzemplarz 2-gi, Opis Wizerunków Dworów, Rezydencji, Zamków Polskich, (Tom 2) M. Jałowiecki (Folder 5: 3)
  - Katalog Kolekcji, M. Jałowiecki (Folder 5: 4)
  - Dwór Polski, Opis Kolekcji Wizerunków, M. Jałowiecki (Folder 5: 5)
  - "The Polish Countryhouses," Major M. Med. Jałowiecki, Index: England 1948-50 (Folder 5: 6)
  - "The Polish Countryhouses," Major M. Med. Jałowiecki, Index: A Commentary on the Collection of Watercolors, England 1948-50 (Folder 5: 7)
  - "Opis Wizerunków, Dworów, Rezydencji, Zamków Polskich,"M. Jałowiecki (Tom 1) (Folder 6: 1)
  - "Dwór Polski, Opis Koleckji, Wizerunków,"M. Jałowiecki (Tom 2) (Folder 6: 2)
  - "Opis Kolekcji Wizerunków,"M. Jałowiecki, (Tom 3) (Folder 6: 3)
  - "Dwór Polski, Katalog Główny," M. Perejasławski-Jałowiecki (Folder 6: 4)
  - "Dwór Polski, Skorowidz Nazw, Miejscowości w Kolekcji,"M. Jałowieckiego (Folder 6: 5)
  - "Skorowidz Nazw, Miejscowości w Kolekcji,"M. Jałowieckiego (Folder 6: 6)
  - "Spis Nazwisk, w Opisach Kolekcji,"M. Jałowieckiego (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Dwór Polski, Spis Nazwisk w Opisach Kolekcji,"M. Jałowiecki (Folder 7: 1)
  - "Dwór Polski, Katalog,"M. Jałowieckiego (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Dwór Polski, Katalog Glówny,"M. Perejasławski-Jałowiecki, 1948-1949. This version of the document provided the item list of watercolor drawings below. (Folder 7: 3)
- Writings, undated. (Box 7-8)
  Miscellaneous writings.
  - "Almanach Ziemiaństwa,"Część 1 (Folder 7: 4)
  - "Almanach Ziemiaństwa,"Część 2 (Folder 7: 5)
  - "Almanach Ziemiaństwa,"(Tom 3) Ruś (Folder 7: 6)
  - "Ruś Materiały" (Folder 7: 7)
  - "Architekci i Budowniczowie Siedzib Wiejskich,"M. Jałowiecki (Folder 7: 8)
  - "Dzieje Wołynia" (Folder 7: 9)
  - "Dwór Polski, Architekci i Budowniczowie Siedzib Wiejskich,"M. Jałowiecki (Folder 8: 1)
  - "Wielkie Księstwo, Litewskie Materiały," M. Jałowiecki (Folder 8: 2)
- Watercolor drawings (Box 9-20)
  Contains more than one thousand watercolored pencil drawings by Jałowiecki, including drawings of historic manor houses and palaces in historic Poland-Lithuania, covering not only present-day Poland and Lithuania, but Belarus, as well as much of Ukraine and Latvia. Jałowiecki's ancestral manor of Sylgudyszki (Lithuanian, Saldutiskis) as it looked before the ravages of the two world wars and half century of Soviet occupation, is one of the manors depicted.
  Arranged numerically, with numbers missing or duplicated. Numbers and titles taken directly from the index identified as most complete in box 7 folder 3.
  Numbers without watercolor drawings: 4, 7, 14, 15, 16, 24, 170, 176, 222, 432, 438, 516, 529, 532, 575, 618, 733, 867, 923, 941, 953, 954, 1087, 1155
  Numbers duplicated in watercolor drawings (duplicate images or two views): 2, 331, 375, 524, 530, 541, 865, 937, 942, 943, 957, 958, 959, 962, 973, 1151, 1152, 1155
  - "R.I.P. Lithuanian country manor, winter 1961-1962"depicting wolves howling in a landscape of cut trees and abandoned ruins of country homes (Box 9)
  - 1. KAMIEŃ Dwór. pow. kaliski, Zofji z Romockich Perejasławskiej-Jałowieckiej (Box 9)
  - 2. KOŹMINEK Dwór. pow. kaliski, Marji z Mieleckich Handtkowej (two drawings) (Box 9)
  - 3. LECIESZYN Dwór. Stefan Czarnocki - Zofia z Domańskich (Box 9)
  - 4. [no drawing] (Box 9)
  - 5. UJAZD Pałac. Wlkp. ze Szczyttów hr Żółtowska (Box 9)
  - 6. KUROZWĘKI Pałac. pow. buski ziemia kielecka. Paweł Popiel - Zofia z Mańkowskich (Box 9)
  - 7. [no drawing] (Box 9)
  - 8. ŻEMŁOSLAW Pałac. pow oszmiański ziemia wileńska. Janiny z hr Ostrowskich hr Umiastowskiej Milewskiej (Box 9)
  - 9. HORODYSZCZE Dwór. pow. ihumeński. ziemia mińska. Zofji z Mierzejewskich Wańkowiczowej (Box 9)
  - 10. JASIONNA pow. sieradzki. Bronisław Gutowski - Maria z Jażdżewskich (Box 9)
  - 11. MOŁODÓW Pałac. pow. piński. Konstanty i Henryk Skirmuntowie (Box 9)
  - 12. PORZECZE Dwór. pow. piński. Senator Roman Skirmunt (Box 9)
  - 13. ŻELAZOWA WOLA pow. grójecki. ongiś Szopenów. Miejsce urodzenia Fryderyka (Box 9)
  - 14-16. [no drawings] (Box 9)
  - 17. KRASÓW Dwór. Fundacja Abrahamowicza woj. lwowskie. Kurator Roman hr. Zaleski - Krystyna z Woźniakowskich (Box 9)
  - 18. SŁOCINA Dwór. Małopolska Wsch. Maurycy Chłapowski - Anna z bar. Brunickich. (Box 9)
  - 19. NIEDZICA Zamek. Małopolska. hr Solomon (Box 9)
  - 20. CYRKLISZKI Pałac. pow. Święciany, ziemia wileńska. Z Chalcza Chaleccy (Box 9)
  - 21. SZEMETOWSZCZYZNA Dwór. pow. Święciany, ziemia wileńska. Bolesław Skirmunt - Gabriela z Chłapowskich (Box 9)
  - 22. ROMANISZKI Dwór. pow. Święciany, ziemia wileńska. Ignacy Dowgiałło - Helena z Wagnerów (Box 9)
  - 23. GOZDOWO pow. Płocki, ziemia warszawska. Krzętowscy (Box 9)
  - 24. [no drawing] (Box 9)
  - 25. CHOCEŃ Dwór. pow. Włocławek, Kujawy. Władysław Chudzyński - Maria z Jaroszyńskich (Box 9)
  - 26. POŁĄGA Pałac pow. Telsze, Żmudź. Feliks hr Tyszkiewicz (Box 9)
  - 27. KRETYNGA Pałac. pow. Telsze, Żmudź, Aleksander hr Tyszkiewicz - Maria z hr. Pusłowskich (Box 9)
  - 28. ISLAUŻ Pałac. ziemia suwalska, Maria z hr Pusłowskich hr Tyszkiewiczowa (Box 9)
  - 29. WIELIKI Dwór. pow. poniewieski, Wincenty Józefowicz - /N/ z Kupściów (Box 9)
  - 30. RYDZYNA Pałac. Wielkopolska. ongiś ks Sulkowskich, ostatnio rządowe (Box 9)
  - 31. IWONICZ Pałac. Małopolska. Bogdan hr Załuski (Box 9)
  - 32. BOŁSZOWCE Pałac. pow. Stanisławów, Młp Wsch. Pułk. dr. Kornel Krzeczunowicz - Helena z hr. Lubienieckich (Box 9)
  - 33. OŻENIN Dwór. Wołyń. Stefan Jełowicki - Cecylia z hr Steckich (Box 9)
  - 34. PORYCK Pałac. Wołyń. Stanisław hr Czacki - Jadwiga z hr Broel Platerów (Box 9)
  - 35. SMORDWA Pałac Wołyń. Aleksander hr Ledóchowski - Maria z hr Orłowskich (Box 9)
  - 36. ZALESIE Dwór. pow. wilejski. Jan hr Mohl - Maria z Oskierków. (Box 9)
  - 37. TURYCZANY Pałac Wołyń. Tadeusz Krzyżanowski (Box 9)
  - 38-39. MŁYNÓW Pałac. Wołyń. Mieczysław hr Chodkiewicz - /N/ z hr Steckich (Box 9)
  - 40. RÓWNE Pałac. Wołyń. Kazimierz ks Lubomirski (Box 9)
  - 41. WIŚNIOWIEC Pałac. Wołyń, ongiś ks Wiśniowieckich (Box 9)
  - 42. CHYLIN Pałac. pow. koniński woj. poznańskie, Ludwik Pułaski - Janina z Janta-Półczynskich (Box 9)
  - 43. CIELEŚNICA Pałac Podlasie, Stanisław bar Rozenwerth - Julja z ks Mirskich (Box 9)
  - 44. LUSZYN Pałac. pow. Sochaczewski, ziemia warszawska, Szambelan Stanisław Godlewski - Zofia z Krzymuskich (Box 9)
  - 45. SIENIEŻYCE Dwór. pow. nowogrodzki, Jan Baliński Jundziłł - Maria z Niezabytowskich (Box 9)
  - 46. SARNÓW Dwór. Podlasie, Roman Dmochowski (Box 9)
  - 47. JAGODNE Dwór. Podlasie, Edward Szydłowski (Box 9)
  - 48. OŁYKA Zamek. Wołyń, z ks. Sapiehów - Pelagia ks Radziwiłłowa (Box 9)
  - 49. WYSZKI Pałac. pow Dyneburg, Inflanty, Heronim hr. Mohl - /N/ z Boonholdów (Box 9)
  - 50. DROHOBUŻ Ruiny zamku. Wołyń (Box 9)
  - 51. BARANÓW Zamek. Małopolska, Roman Dolański - Jadwiga z Mniszech-Tchórznickich (Box 9)
  - 52. DOWMONTY Dwór. pow. Kiejdany, ziemia kowieńska, Jan Minkiewicz (Box 9)
  - 53. CIECHANÓW Ruiny zamku. ziemia warszawska (Box 9)
  - 54. STRZAŁKI Dwór. Małopolska Wsch. Rotmistrz Józef Rudnicki - /N/ z Okulskich (Box 9)
  - 55. HORODNO Pałac. pow. Lidzki, Ada Generałowa Kondratowicz (Box 9)
  - 56. MIROWSZCZYZNA Dwór. pow. nowogródzki, Jan Strawiński - Alina z Montwiłłów (Box 9)
  - 57. BRZEŻANY Zamek. Małopolska Wsch, ongiś Sieniawskich, Potockich...... (Box 9)
  - 58. ŻÓŁKIEW Zamek. Małopolska, ongiś Żółkiewskich, Sobieskich..... (Box 9)
  - 59. ŚWIRZ Zamek, fragment. Małopolska Wsch, z hr Lamezanów de Salins - generałowej hr Komorowskiej (Box 9)
  - 60. SOSNOWICA Dwór. Podlasie, Teodor Libiszowski - Pelagia z Iżyckich (Box 9)
  - 61. KRASNOBRÓD Dwór. Prezes Kazimierz Fudakowski - Maria z Kicińskich (Box 9)
  - 62. ROGÓW Dwór zabytkowy. Małopolska k/ Opatowca nad Wisłą, Karol hr Ogiński Skorzewski - Janina z ks Druckich - Lubeckich (Box 9)
  - 63. GRODOWICE Dwór. Małopolska k/ Felsztyna, Karol bar Czecz - Romana z ks Sułkowskich (Box 9)
  - 64. STARE SIOŁO Zamek. Małopolska Wsch, ongiś Sobieskich ostatnio Potockich (Box 9)
  - 65. ZAWAŁÓW Zamek. Małopolska Wsch. Raczyńskich (Box 9)
  - 66. NIEBORÓW Pałac. pow. Łowicki, Janusz ks Radziwiłł - Anna z ks Lubomirskich (Box 9)
  - 67. POSADOWO Pałac. Wielkopolska, Stanisław hr Łącki - Emilia z hr Mielżyńskich (Box 9)
  - 68. GOŁUCHÓW Zamek. Wielkopolska pow. Pleszew, Adam ks. Czartoryski - Ludwika z hr Krasińskich (Box 9)
  - 69. KURNIK Pałac. Wielkopolska, Władysław hr Zamoyski (Box 9)
  - 70. LUBOSTROŃ Pałac. Wielkopolska, Maria z ks Radziwiłłów (Box 9)
  - 71. ROGALIN Pałac. Wielkopolska, Roger hr Raczyński - Helena z Rohozińskich (Box 9)
  - 72. KRASICZYN Zamek. Małopolska, Leon ks Sapieha - Katarzyna z hr Potockich (Box 9)
  - 73. KRASICZYN Zamek. Małopolska (Box 9)
  - 74. WINNOGÓRA Pałac. Wielkopolska, Stanisław Mańkowski - /N/ z hr Zyberg - Platerów (Box 9)
  - 75. SAPOHÓW Pałac. Małopolska Wsch. hr Koziebrodzki (Box 9)
  - 76. LESKO Pałac. Małopolska Wsch., August hr. Krasicki - Izabella z hr. Wodzickich (Box 9)
  - 77. SIELEC Pałac. Wielkopolska, Józef bar Unrug (Box 9)
  - 78. PIEKARY Dwór. pow. krakowski, Witold Miljewski - /N/ z Sieheniów (Box 9)
  - 79. WIELGOLAS Dwór. pow. Rawsko - Mazowiecki, Bogdan Wyleżyński - Celina z Lesznowskich (Box 9)
  - 80. BROSZKÓW Dwór. ziemia kielecka, Buynów (Box 9)
  - 81. CHYBY Dwór. Wielkopolska, prof. Bernard Massey - /N/ z Bittnerów (Box 9)
  - 82. SIENIAWA Dworek. Małopolska, Podkarpacie, Róża Zduniowa (Box 9)
  - 83. RABA WYŻNA Dwór. Podkarpacie, pow. Nowy Targ, własność Głowińskich (Box 9)
  - 84. JABŁONNA Pałac. pow. warszawski, Maurycy hr Potocki (Box 9)
  - 85. PSZCZYNA Zamek. Śląsk, Bolko ks na Pszczynie / Furst zu Pless / (Box 9)
  - 86. GÓRKI WIELKIE Dwór. Śląsk, nabyty po pierwszej wojnie przez Tadeusza Kossaka (Box 9)
  - 87. GRODZIEC Zamek. Śląsk, dr Ernest Habicht - Amelia z Niemczańskich (Box 9)
  - 88. SZYCHOWCE Dwór. ziemia lubelska, Kazimierz Rulikowski radca T.K.Z. - Jadwiga z Łączyńskich (Box 9)
  - 89. PORHOWA Dwór. Mał. Wsch., Józef bar. Hoendorf - Zofia z hr Dzieduszyckich (Box 9)
  - 90. BURSZTYN Pałac. Małopolska, Karolina z ks Jabłonowskich baronowa Heidel (Box 9)
  - 91. ZUŁÓW Ostatki dworu po spaleniu. pow. Święciany, ziemia wileńska, ongiś Józefa Piłsudskiego - Marji z Billewiczow rodziców Marszałka Piłsudskiego (Box 9)
  - 92. PIKIELISZKI Dwór. pod Wilnem, Folwark ofiarowany przez naród Józefowi Piłsudskiemu Marszałkowi Polski ożenionemu z Aleksandrą ze Szczerbińskich (Box 9)
  - 93. SABNIE Dwór. Podlasie, Józef Moniuszko - Józefa z Mniszech - Tchórznickich (Box 9)
  - 94. SYŁGUDYSZKI Dwór. pow. wilkomierski, na rdzennej Litwie, Generał Bolesław Perejasławski - Jałowiecki - Aniela z Witkiewiczów (Box 9)
  - 95. KUKUCISZKI Dwór (Box 9)
  - 96. ZAOSIE Dworek. pod Nowogródkiem, Miejsce urodzenia Adama Mickiewicza - własność rodziców, Adama Mikołaja Mickiewicza i Barbary z Majewskich (Box 9)
  - 97. TUHANOWICZE Murowanka (oficyna). ziemia nowogródzka, Marji Tuhanowskiej (Box 9)
  - 98. UBIEL Dwór. pow. ihumeński, ziemia mińska, Moniuszków / Miejsce urodzenia Stanisława Moniuszki (Box 9)
  - 99. GIEJSTUNY Dwór. pow. oszmiański, ziemia wileńska, tu się urodził Antoni Odyniec przyjaciel Mickiewicza, córka Chometowska sprzedała dobra na parcelacje. Dwór został rozebrany (Box 9)
  - 100. FIRLEJEWSZCZYZNA Dworek. pod Lublinem miejsce urodzenia Wincentego Pola (Box 10)
  - 101. MERECZOWSZCZYZNA Dwór. pow. Słonimsk miejsce urodzenia Tadeusza Kościuszki własność Władysława hr Puslowskiego - Krystyny s ks Pignaletti (Box 10)
  - 102. SZARKI Zagroda. pow. wiłkomierski, ziemia kowieńska Krystyny Malinowskiej (Box 10)
  - 103. CZOMBRÓW Dwór. pow. Nowogródzki Karpowiczów (Box 10)
  - 104. TROKI Ruiny zamku. ziemia wileńska (Box 10)
  - 105. NOWOGRÓDEK Ruiny zamku (Box 10)
  - 106. WERKI Pałac, fragment Leonida z ks Radziwiłłów ks. Witgenstein a ostatnio ks. Hohenlohe, ożeniony z ks. Witgenstein (Box 10)
  - 107. HRYNCEWICZE Dwór. ziemia wileńska (Box 10)
  - 108. DERESZEWICZE Dwór. pow. rzeczycki, Polesie Antoni Kieniewicz - Maria Magdalena z hr. Rabowskich (Box 10)
  - 109. TYNIOWICE Dwór. Małopolska Leonia z Malinowskich Grodzicka (Box 10)
  - 110. GIERANONY Dwór. pow. Oszmiana, ziemia wileńska Szymon Meysztowicz - Antonina z Dzierżykraj Morawskich (Box 10)
  - 111. Ziemia Wileńska (Box 10)
  - 112. DOBROWLANY Pałac. pow. święciański, ziemia wileńska Zygmunt Chomiński - /N/ z Horwattów (Box 10)
  - 113. OLSZEW Dwór. pow. Święciany, ziemia wileńska Aleksander Chomiński poseł do Rady Państwa - Jadwiga z Horwattów (Box 10)
  - 114. WOJTKUSZKI Pałac. pow. Wiłkomierz, na Litwie Kowieńskiej Stanisław Michał hr Kossakowski - Maria z Bispingów (Box 10)
  - 115. NEKLA Pałac. Wielkopolska Franciszek hr Żółtowski (Box 10)
  - 116. DERECZYN Pałac. ziemia grodzieńska ongiś ks. Sapiehów (Box 10)
  - 117. POSTAWY Pałac. pow. Święciany, ziemia wileńska Raynold hr Przeździecki (Box 10)
  - 118. DZIEWIĄTKOWICZE Oficyna Jan Ślizień (Box 10)
  - 119. BOREJKOWSZCZYZNA Dworek folwarku należącego do klucza Kojrańskiego Hr. Tyszkiewiczów - ongiś dzierżawa Wincentego Pola (Box 10)
  - 120. WERKI Pałac. pod Wilnem z ks. Witgenstein ks. Hohenlohe (Box 10)
  - 121. SNÓW Dwór. pow. nowogródzki Rdułtowskich - ostatnio bar Hartingów (Box 10)
  - 122. NIEŚWIEŻ Zamek. ziemia słucka Albrecht ks Radziwiłł (Box 10)
  - 123. NIEŚWIEŻ Zamek. ziemia słucka (Box 10)
  - 124. WOROŃCZA Dwór. pow. nowogródzki Izabella z Mierzejewskich Lubańska (Box 10)
  - 125. KRĘGNÓW Dwór. pow. Przasnysz Irena z Tuchołków Mańkowska (Box 10)
  - 126. HOŁYNKA Dwór. ziemia grodzieńska (Box 10)
  - 127. HOŁYNKA Dwór ziemia nowogródzka (Box 10)
  - 128. KREWO Ruiny zamku. pow. Oszmiana (Box 10)
  - 129. WORNIANY Dwór. pow. oszmiański, ziemia wileńska Józef Mineyko (Box 10)
  - 130. MARCHWACZ Pałac. ziemia kaliska Marszalek koronny Wacław Niemojowski - Zofia z hr Szembeków (Box 10)
  - 131. PONIEWIEŻYK Dwór. pow. kowieński Korewo-Babiańska (Box 10)
  - 132. POGINIE (Box 10)
  - 133. MARYWIL Dwór. pow. kowieński Tadeusz Zenowicz (Box 10)
  - 134. ? Dwór. pow. Nowogródzki (Box 10)
  - 135. CZERWONOGRÓD Pałac. Małopolska Wsch. Maria z hr Zamoyskich ks Lubomirska (Box 10)
  - 136. ŚLEDZIEJEWICE Pałac. Małopolska Larisz - Niedzielscy (Box 10)
  - 137. BECZKANY Dwór. pow. kowieński Butlerów (Box 10)
  - 138. NIAŃKÓW Dwór. pow. nowogródzki Zofji hr Umiastowskiej - Milewskiej (zagrabiony przez osadników i rozparcelowany) (Box 10)
  - 139. MIECZOWNICA Dwór. pow. koniński ziemia Kaliska Janusz Chrzanowski - Marja z Brzeskich (Box 10)
  - 140. SIESIKI Zamek. pow Wiłkomierz, na Litwie rdzennej Dominik Dowgiałło - Anna z hr Chodkiewiczów (Box 10)
  - 141. KOŚCIELNA WIEŚ Dwór pow. kaliski Ludwik Krzeczunowicz - Stefania z Chrzanowskich (Box 10)
  - 142. POD JEDLAMI Willa w Zakopanem Michał Pawlikowski - Aniela z Wolskich (Box 10)
  - 143. KRÓLIKARNIA Pałac pod Warszawą Marta z hr Pusłowskich hr Krasińska (Box 10)
  - 144. LEWKÓW Pałac. pow. Ostrów Wielkopolska Jan Lipski - Antonina z hr Żółtowskich (Box 10)
  - 145. NAWRA Dwór. Pomorze Jan Szczaniecki - Irena z Cichowskich (Box 10)
  - 146. ORŁOWO Pałac. Pomorze Jerzy Sląski - Katarzyna z hr Mycielskich (Box 10)
  - 147. NIEDŹWIEDŹ Dwór. Pomorze Wacław Mieszkowski (Box 10)
  - 148. KLONÓWKA Pomorze Wacław Rudowski - Katarzyna ze Stryjewskich (Box 10)
  - 149. KOMIEROWO Pałac. Pomorze Tomasz ordynat Komierowski - Róża z hr Zamoyskich (Box 10)
  - 150. GOŁUB Zamek. Pomorze (Box 10)
  - 151. JABŁONOWO Pałac. Pomorze Zygmunt Narzymski (Box 10)
  - 152. WEYHEROWO Pałac. Pomorze hr Kayserling (Box 10)
  - 153. RZUCEWO Pałac Pomorze hr v. Below (Box 10)
  - 154. ŚWIECIE Zamek. Pomorze (Box 10)
  - 155. TRZEBCZ Pałac. Pomorze Ludwik Śląski (Box 10)
  - 156. GNIEW Zamek. Pomorze (Box 10)
  - 157. WILANÓW Pałac pod Warszawa Ksawery hr Branicki - Anna z hr Potockich (Box 10)
  - 158. MALBORK Zamek. Prusy Wsch. (Box 10)
  - 159. TYNIEC Opactwo pod Krakowem (Box 10)
  - 160. GIEŁGUDYSZKI Zamek. ziemia kowieńska ongiś rodziny Giełgudów (Box 10)
  - 161. GUŁTOWY Pałac. Wielkopolska Alfred hr Bniński - Maria z hr Skorzewskich (Box 10)
  - 162. MIKIELEWSZCZYZNA Dwór. pow. Białystok Karol Wańkowicz - Kazimira z bar Romerów (Box 10)
  - 163. PAULINÓW. Dwór pow. baranowicki Florian Bochwic (Box 10)
  - 164. HOŁONETY Dwór pow. Wiłkomierz rdzenna Litwa Ewa Rudominianka (Box 10)
  - 165. DZIAŁDÓW Zamek. Pomorze (Box 10)
  - 166. GOŁKÓW Dwór podwarszawski ongiś baronów Danglów kareciarzy nadwornych Króla Stanisława (Box 10)
  - 167. CZYŻEW Pałac woj. sandomierskie Józef Targowski min pełn.- Elżbieta z Deskurów (Box 10)
  - 168. HRUSZOWA Dwór. pow. kobryński, ziemi brzeskiej Znakomitej autorki Marji Rodziewiczówny (Box 10)
  - 169. ZAMEK PRZECŁAWSKI Małopolska Zamek Stanisław hr Rey - Jadwiga z hr Branickich (Box 10)
  - 170. [no drawing] (Box 10)
  - 171. ANTONINY Fragment zabudowań Wołyń Józef hr Potocki - Helena z ks Radziwiłłów (Box 10)
  - 172. GOLEJEWKO Pałac Wielkopolska Janusz hr Czarnecki - Romana z Czarnowskich (Box 10)
  - 173. GÓRZNO Pałac. Wielkopolska. Kazimierz Lipski - Maria z Komarów (Box 10)
  - 174. MIŁOSŁAW Pałac. Wielkopolska. Władysław Kościelski - Monika z Krystyńskich (Box 10)
  - 175. SZYPIANY Dwór. pow Borysowski, ziemia mińska. Paweł Wańkowicz - Anna z Potockich (Box 10)
  - 176. [no drawing] (Box 10)
  - 177. SAWICZE Zameczek. pow. słucki, ziemia mińska. Prezes Edward Woyniłłowicz - Olimpja z Uzułłowskich (Box 10)
  - 178. NAROWLA Pałac nad Prypecią ziemia mozyrska, Polesie. Edward Horwatt - Jadwiga z Oskierków (Box 10)
  - 179. BARBARÓW Pałac nad Prypecia pow. mozyrski, Polesie. Aleksander Horwatt - Jadwiga z hr Krasickich (Box 10)
  - 180. CZERWONY DWÓR Pałac pod Kownem. Benedykt hr Tyszkiewicz - Róża z hr Branickich (Box 10)